look now there is a threat of
смотри сейчас там грозит
NVI Yes yes they are called all sorts of streets
НВИ Да да их называют всякими улицы
are called squares
называют площади
are called
называют
Hello
Здравствуйте Вы
where are you from
откуда Из
Yakutia My mother is Sakha
якути У меня мама Саха
[music]
[музыка]
Yes I
Да
sympathize my father is Russian And my mother is
Сочувствую отец русский А мама
Sakha Where is
Саха Откуда
she from somewhere some village near Aldan
она где-то какой-то посёлок возле алдана
but I don't remember which one
но я не помню какой
there is definitely gold there my father worked in
точно там золото оно отец работал на
gold mining and she worked there they
золотодобыче и она там работала они там
met there I was born I was born
познакомились я родился Я родился
in Yakutia but my birth certificate says
в Якутии но ня рождени пишет
Yakutsk I don't know how it can well
Якутск я не знаю как может
maybe Well
може Ну
not the birth certificate
не свидетельство о рождении
says Russian Soviet
написано Российская Советская
Federative Socialist Republic
Федеративная Социалистическая Республика
city of Yakutsk
город Якутск
Why is it a certificate when  born in what
Да почему свиде когда родился в каком го
year During the Soviet
год При Советском
Union the public there wrote I USSR Yakut
созе публика там пише я СССР Якутский
Autonomous SCI no u No there was I I
автономный сци нет у Нет там было я я
will say so to me Someone from Yakutia also told me
скажу значит мне Мне тоже говорил кто-то
yes eh there were several
из Якутии да э там было несколько
forms of these someone wrote eh
бланков этих у кого-то писалось ээ
just RSFSR and  city ​​and someone
просто РСФСР и город а у кого-то
wrote r Russian Soviet
писалась р Российская Советская
Socialist Republic
Социалистическая Республика
Yes Republic of Yakutia or  somehow she
Да республика Якутия или как-то она там
was written there and then Yakutsk And I had it
писалась и тогда Якутск А у меня
written down
записано
by hand before they described it like because
раньше от руки описывали типа потому что
I still have such a
у меня ещ такое свидетельство
green certificate and it was written by
зелёненькое и вписано от
hand here to
руки сюда
be nya
быть ня
written autonomous social republic of the Soviet Union
написа автономна соци республика
What year were you
сове Вы какого года
born
рождения
se see
се види у
I have already written No  I know No no
меня ле уже писали Не знаю Нет нет У
My wife of 1982 also
моей жены восемьдесят второго года тоже
I have SS written I understood yes Oh and then
я СС написан понял да О а потом
it turns out that you don't live in Germany
получается что что не вы в Германии
yes yes yes I was three years old and my
живёте да да да мне было три года и
parents left from there Yes
уехали оттуда родители уехали оттуда Да
they left for Germany not Not at first Well that's
в Германию уехали не Не сначала Ну это
still Soviet  The Union then it was impossible to
ещё Советский Союз тогда нельзя было в
go to Germany we went then to Kazakhstan
Германию уехать уехали тогда в Казахстан
to Kazakhstan to work we lived in the
в Казахстан на работу мы жили в сем
Palatinate already when the Soviet Union
палатинский уже когда Советский Союз
collapsed we went to
развалился то выехали в
Germany father father probably German yes well
Германию отец отец наверное немец да ну
yes he was kind of Russian but he was a
да он как бы русский был но он был
Volga German he Volga German he
Поволжский немец он Поволжский немец он
was exiled to Kazakhstan then he went to
был сослан в Казахстан потом он поехал
work in Aldan for gold there he
работать на Алдан на это на золото там
met his mother there I was born but
познакомился с мамой Там я родился но
there were very bad conditions and cold
там очень Условия были плохие и холодно
and  and they returned it
и это и вернули
to Kazakhstan And then we moved to
в Казахстан И потом мы переехали в
Germany And how are things with you now Well,
Германию Да как там у вас сейчас Ну у
you seem to have a rich republic gold
вас вроде богатая республика золото
diamonds Yes, you have everything, well, you live richly
алмазы Да всё есть у ну богато живёте
How much is your
сколько у вас
salary My salary is
зарплаты заплата у меня
50,000 500
50.000 500
dollars from the dollar
долларов с долла
count vabo Soviet la Kato Banner
счита вабо Советский ла Като Знамя
Soviet or what is
Советское или что
it yes and show me
это да а покажите мне
interestingly
интересно
Advanced for high
Передовое за высокие показатели
performance in the plan in socialist
выполнения плано в социалистическом
competition Yes you
соревновании Да это вы
won it It was a long time ago Under the Soviet
выиграли Это давно было При Советском
Union it is
Союзе
interesting to win well so you Under the
выиграть интересно ну так вы При
Soviet Union were not a worker you
Советском Союз не работником были это вы
already bought it somewhere and then Yes no  this one
уже где-то купили да потом Да нет этот
didn't buy this historical rarity such
не купил этот исторический раритет такой
And
А
whose village village village village village used
чей село село село село село раньше
to win flags were given like these and that
побеждали флаги давали вот такие а то
is your village your village received
есть ваше село ваша деревня получила
this flag Yes And are you now the head of the
этот флаг Да А вы сейчас глава
village council or what happens No I'm
сельсовета или что получается Нет я
just a security guard security guard of what DK club
просто охранник охранник чего ДК клуб
house cult Mago  House of Culture House of
дом культу Маго Дом Культуры дом
Culture - it's in the village, yes, it turns out
культуры - это в селе да получается
Well, somewhere around 800
Ну где-то 800
residents, zhite And what is this north south of
жителей жите А это какая север юг
Yakutia, this is how  they say to the middle of
Якутии это как говорится до середина
Yakutia Yakutsk we have 200
якути Якутска у нас 200
km this is
км это
a lot a lot a lot of
много много много
LDA there is not much
лда там неско
somewhere And what is there in your house of culture
где-то А что в вашем доме культуре есть
like that
такого т
Yes we have nothing
Да ничего нет у
Well
нас Ну
how what What does it mean that you have
как что Что значит что у вас есть
show me what the house of culture in
показать как выглядит дом культуры в
Yakutia looks like  interestingly this is my homeland
якути мне интересно это моя родина
after all let's do it
всё-таки давай
like this yes now
вот так да сейчас
we
нас вот
just passed the New Year this So
так только Новый год прошёл этот Так
normal normal scene Oh they
нормальный нормальная сцена О тут
celebrated here Okay I understand yesterday the
праздновали Хорошо я так понимаю вчера
children celebrated yesterday the children celebrated
дети праздновали вчера дети праздновали
Yeah And so the tower for
Угу А так вышка для
this Tomorrow here we will set the table here for the
это Завтра вот столик будем здесь
holiday  will be And what about the
накладывать праздник будет А что за
50 years
пра 50 лет
Well, where was the state farm founded and 70 years old
Ну где основался совхоз а 70 лет
state farm this
совхоз этот
costume designer now
костюмер
And you are like in Germany well
сечас А вас как в Германии хорошо
Now your ceiling does not leak here in the
Сейчас у вас потолок не протекает тут в
club no it does not leak
клубе не не протекает
we do not leak and are there toilets in the
нас не протекает а а туалеты есть в
club Well or
клубе Ну или
not There are and  can you show what toilets
нету Есть а можете показать как туалеты
look like in
выглядят в
clubs They say that in Russia
клубах Говорят что в России унитазов
there are no toilets
нету
there we
там у нас
understand that in your case it
понял это у вас
turns out that this is a village near some
получается это посёлок возле какого-то
mining plant  No, we don't
добывающего комбината Да нет у нас не
extract
добываю
the combine, it's just a
комбина просто полово
small village, there is no, I'm still young, so I
маленькая де есть не я ещё молодой то я
won't get married yet. And how old are you, how old are you?
так не женюсь пока А сколько те лет
43 Well, in Germany,
43 Ну у нас в Германии только к
we only start families when we're fifty, so for now,
пятидесяти мы семьи заводим то так пока
for ourselves first,
для себя сначала
remember, no, no  need now after so
пом не не надо сейчас на после со се
then if now the child will be so
потом если сейчас ребёнок будет так
how many of you are somewhere 5060 already an old man
сколько тебя где-то 5060 уже стариком же
you will not see grandchildren
будешь внуков не посмотришь
Well
Ну
Dado and how many do you have
Дадо а а у вас сть сколько
Well somewhere
Ну где-то
23 the oldest is
23 само старшему
23 the middle daughter is
23 средней дочке
son
сыну
17 well there that's the most  junior first grade
17 ну там это самый младший первый класс
somewhere se This is from how old
гдето се Это от скольки
is one wife
жн одна жена
she is not tired of giving
она не замучилась
birth no we are thinking of having a seventh one And
рожать нет думаем ещё седьмого завести А
how
сколько ей
old is she somewhere
лет где-то
43 I understand And what does she
43 понял А она кем
work as a
работает
veterinarian I understand I
ветеринар понял
wonder Everything is fine with us everything is
интересно Всё нормально у нас всё
fine we need M pain to have children mda
нормально надо М боль дете ть мда
ourselves  on the farm koro
сами у на хозяйство коро
pig pork
сви свинину
eat you are not
едите вы не
Muslims not we are not Muslims
мусульмани не мы не мусульмане
not
не
me I
мын
understand Rene
понял Рене
new church to put up for us this is the head
новый церковь поставить у нас это голова
and you did not think that it turns out  Russia
а вы это не думали что получается Россия
takes money from your gold and
у вас забирает деньги от золота и
diamonds No, I don't think so Well, it turns out that you
алмазов Нет не думаю ну получается вы
extract everything And everything goes to
всё добывается А всё уходит в
Moscow Well, look, we have
Москву Ну у нас смотри у нас работают и
American companies and European
американские компании европейские
companies working for us, you know That's
компании понимаешь
right Yes, but Moscow gets the money for them
Правильно Да но деньги за них получает
and not you, not us either  will remain de
Москва а не вы не у нас тоже остатся де
Yes but little that is Moscow does not
Да но мало то есть Москва ничего не
extract anything for itself but takes everything from the
добывает себе но всё забирает у
people
людей
that diamonds gold are mined in Moscow
что в Москве добываются алмазы золото
No there are just companies registered
Нет там просто регистрируются компании
that's
вот и
all Well everywhere it's the same everywhere Well so
всё Ну везде же так везде же Ну так
Yakuts work on the ground
якутс по земле работа
That is it turns out that you could  to
То есть получается что вы да могли бы
live richly as in the Emirates And you live in poverty
жить богато как в Эмиратах А живёте бед
We never do not And why do we never
Мы никогда не не А почему мы никогда не
know why Because if we have
знаешь почему Потому что у нас если мы
500,000 from us we can't live like a
от нас же 500.000 мы же не можем как бы
world
мирата
Yakuts only 500,000 you understand The Earth is
якутов только 500.000 понимаешь Земля у
several million kilometers long for us
нас несколько миллионов километров
you understand So  stop on what big
понимаешь Так стоп на какой большой
land look again
земле ещё раз смотри
yakuti so
якути так Республика
Sakha Republic 3 million
Саха 3 млн
population Why do we have 3 ml Miln
населения Почему 3 мл у нас Милн
population look 3 ml
населения посмотри 3 мл
pori Wikipedia Nano
пори Википеди Нано
not 500000  Yakuts you know
не 500000 якутов понимаешь
there are 500 Yakuts there you have more Yakuts
якутов там 500 увас у вас якутов больше
more than half of the population of Yakuts according to the
больше половины населения якутов по
census there are no we only have 500,000 don't
переписи нет у нас только 500.000 не
look it's more than Estonia more than
смотри Это больше чем Эстония больше чем
Estonia Why can Estonia be
Эстония Почему Эстония может быть
independent And you are
независимая А вы
not Estonia is a rich country richer than
не Эстония богатая страна богаче чем
Yakutia yes
Якутия да
in the research institute the minimum wage is 700 euros  and
внии минимальная зарплата 700 евро а у
you have a salary of 50,500 euros No, not
вас вот зарплата 50 500 евро Да не
Estonia, look, look, in Estonia, the
Эстонии смотри смотрите в Эстонии убл
population is bigger than ours, no, don't look,
население больше чем у нас не не смотри
that is, it turns out that they are
то есть получается что они же они же
working in Europe, you know, they are working in Germany.
Европой работают понимаешь Германии
In short, look, salaries in
работают Короче смотри зарплаты в
Estonia are higher than salaries in Yakutia, that's
Эстонии выше чем зарплаты в Якутии это
for sure. Well,  maybe I'm the same I'm the same
однозначно Ну может быть я же я ж прил
there where the utilities are No well where the
там там где Коммунальный Нет ну там где
utilities are utilities and food
коммунальные коммунальные расходы и еда
and gasoline is cheaper there And electricity
и бензин там что дешевле
Well come on tell me Tell me what
Да и свет Ну давай скажи Скажи мне
the utilities are there
коммунальные расходы там
Don't give me Well in Germany they
какие Не давайте Ну в Германии
paid
Коммунальный там платили
how much for utilities there Our Lord Jesus I  I know that you
сколько Господи наш Иисусе я знаю что
reward everyone according to their
каждому воз даёшь по его
merits. These  people don't seem to deserve to
заслугам Эти люди походу не заслужили
live in wealth
жить в богатстве
I know that you want to make them rich
Я знаю что ты хочешь сделать их богатыми
but they don't want to they
но они не хотят они
sit on their gold and diamond deposits
сидят своей на залежах золота и алмазов
and say We can't be rich we
и говорят Мы не сможем быть богатыми мы
can't live rich we can't
не сможем жить богатыми мы не сможем
live rich I think that they
жить богатыми Я думаю что они этого
deserve it  Yes Amen, I
заслужили Да Аминь
don't have
пока пони тебя не
children yet, I understand that you have no expenses, nothing.
дете понима у тебя не ни расходов ничего
Yes, of course, you will live richly. I have
Да конечно ты будешь жить богато у меня
six children, but we are rich. We live well.
шестеро детей но богаты мы жим нормально
I feed everyone. I dress everyone. They have a
я всех кормлю я всех одеваю у них
phone. Everything
телефон всё
is there. If it weren't for this war in Ukraine, and the war
есть если бы не эта война на Украине да
that the Ukrainians are waging.  tied up Yes, it would have been even
которую украинцы завязали Да было ещё
better if the Americans hadn't
лучше бы не американцы не
tied up and put sticks under the horses
завязали не поставляли палки под кони
Look, we only started living normally
Вот смотри мы нормально жить начали
20 years ago, you know 20 years Yes,
только 20 лет назад понимаете 20 лет Да
that's 0 Boshe, we lived, you know, and now we
это 0 Боше жили понимаешь а сейчас
've started living normally Wait, did I
начали нормально жить подожди я
understand correctly that if the Ukrainians hadn't
правильно понял что если б украинцы не
unleashed this  war you would
развязали эту войну вы б сейчас
live normally now yes of course you
нормально жили да конечно нормально
lived normally isn't that so you went to
жили разве не так то есть вы полезли
fight in Ukraine and still regret that you
воевать в Украину и ещё жалеете что вы
live poorly because the Ukrainians
плохо живёте из-за того что украинцы
unleashed
развязали
war I say I live well I say
войну Я говорю Я неплохо живу я говорю
that I live badly I do not say that I live badly You
что я плохо Я не говорю что я плохо живу
see I say E would live better you
Понимаешь я говорю Е бы лучше жили бы
see If it were not the Ukrainians who
понимаешь Если не украинцы э войну
started the war that is, look again you attacked
начали то есть ещё раз смотри вы напали
Ukraine And now you see that you would
на Украину А теперь видите что вы бы
live better  if the Ukrainians had not started
жили лучше если бы украинцы не начали
the war, we would not have attacked Ukraine, it was
войну не мы не напали на Украину это
Ukraine that attacked No, you
Украина напала Нет вы своими войсками
invaded Ukraine with your troops last
влезли в Украину вче
year Tell me, did Ukraine
году Расскажи Украин
start a war where Russia attacked Russia,
начали войну где на Россию напал Россию
look, now Bandera, Khvicha, Petliura are threatening there
смотри сейчас там грозит бандеру хвича
Yes, yes, they are called all sorts of things Yes,
Петлюру Да да их называют всякими Да
the streets are called squares  call it
улицы называют площади называть потом
Donbass later Yes Donbass began its
Донбасс Да Донбасс начал свою
independence And you are pushing for the
независимость А вы же прёте за
independence of Yakutia yes And why
независимость Якутии да А почему там не
shouldn't it be there no need no need Wait
должно быть не надо не надо Подожди
Listen listen Let's go in order about
Послушай послушай Давай по порядку про
Bandera Petliura Shukhevych Look, you
бандеру Петлюру Шухевича Смотри вот ты
are sitting in Yakutia somewhere where it's freezing in a
сидишь в Якутии где-то там где морозит в
minute  7 and tell me what you know about
мину 7 да и скажи мне что ты знаешь про
Bandera Shukhevych and Petliura  Bandera is a
бандеру Шухевича и Петлюру Бандера - Это
bad person for me oh and that's all I don't need
плохой человек для меня о и всё не надо
everything that Bandera did what did the
мне вся что сделал Бандера что сделал
bando everything everything already Bandera did everything
бандо всё всё уже Бандера делал всё
bad pony what did what specifically what
плохое пони что сделал что конкретно что
specifically did Bandera ho My grandfather
конкретно сделал Бандера хо Мой дед
fought against the fascists and against Bandera
воевал против фашистов и против Бандеры
so Bandera fought against the fascists
так Бандера против фаши воевал не
Bandera is never against fascists tell me tell me
Бандера никогда против фаши скажи скажи
what Bandera did at least one thing
что сделал Бандера хоть одно что сделал
Bandera did Bandera fought together with the
Бандера Бандера воевал вместе с
fascists together with the fascists you know
фашистами вместе с фашистами понимаешь
against the Soviet Union In what
против Советского Союза В какой В какой
battle did Bandera participate I don't need it no
Битве Бандера участвовал мне не надо не
need it no no Tell me from what battle badara
надо нене не Скажи с какой битвы бадара
you look you are Yakuts  were you for Hitler
вы смотри вы якуты были за Гитлера вы
Yakuts were you for Hitler in the war Yes you for
якуты были за Гитлера в войне Да вы за
Hitler Yes my grandfather in the war My grandfather in the
Гитлера Да мой дед на войне Мой дед на
war you Yakuts shot him in the back My
войне вы якуты стреляли ему спину Мой
grandfather in the Soviet Army he told
дед в Советской Армии он рассказывал
said told Yakuts they are all with the
сказал рассказывал якуты они все с
Chinese together no need you
китайцами вместе не надо чепуху
understand nonsense Well show me show me  some order of his
понимаете Ну покажи покажи орден своего
grandfather
деда
look I'm at work How
какой-то смотри я же на работе Как я
can I show my grandfather Are you
могу показать своего деда Ты что ли
seeing Look Here's where your grandfather is on
Видишь Смотри Вот у тебя где твой дед на
what front is your grandfather My grandfather
каком фронте твой дед Мой дед на Берлина
reached Berlin And you Yes my grandfather died at Stalingrad
дошёл А ты Да мой де на Сталинграде
his grandfather is lying in Lviv in Ukraine and what
погиб он дед во льво Украине лежит и что
what you  do you want both my grandfathers
что ты хочешь меня оба деда
died That is, you are you are
погибли То есть ты бе ты ты
childless
бездетный
yes So wait stop How do you know that
да Так подожди стоп Откуда ты знаешь что
these were your grandfathers
это твои деды
Well look my grandmother my grandmother look
Ну смотри моя бабушка моя бабушка смотри
my grandmother Yes she got married 14 years old
моя бабушка Да вышла замуж 14 лет
that you don't need to understand this is normal it was you
что не надо понима это нормально это вы
and the Germans who decided so  that at 14 years old so that
с немцами так решили что в 14 лет чтоб
grandmothers get married
бабушки замуж
You in the Soviet Union Yes in the villages where they got married
Ты в Советском Союзе Да селе де выходили
before 18 gave birth to
раньше 18 рожали
children my grandmother you know
детей моего бабушки понимаешь
after my grandfather died Then she got married a second
после дед погиб Потом вышел замуж второй
time
раз
you know
понимаешь
his first husband died in an accident
его первый муж погиб в одне вне поги
And on my grandfather's side here with my grandfather here
А с дедушкой стороны вот с дедушкой вот
with my grandfather  sides look I remember I
с дедушкой стороны смотри я помню я
read the Memories of Stepan Bandera Yes he
читал Воспоминания Степана Бандеры Да он
wrote that the Yakuts were for the Nazis Yes the
писал что якуты были за нацистов Да
Yakuts were for the Nazis and shot at us
якуты за нацистов и стреляли нам
Ukrainians  Yakuts were never
украинцам никогда не были якуты из
Nazis You also had this
нацистом У вас же ещё была это
Hitler party in Yakutsk No, there
гитлеровская партия в Якутске Нет не
was no what were you at all there was an anti-Soviet
было что ты вообще было антисоветское
Yakut uprising yes for Hitler
восстание якутское было да за Гитлера
When was when was E forty-first year
Когда было когда было Э сорок первый год
when Hitler attacked from this side Yes you
когда Гитлер напал с этой стороны Да вы
attacked together with the Buryats  on the Soviet
с бурятами вместе напали на советские
troops well some look look
войска ну какой-то посмотри посмотри
look these Yakuts in the Wehrmacht service
посмотри эти якуты на службе Вермахта
I saw Yakuts in the Wehrmacht did not
видел я видел якутов в вермахте не
serve Yakuts served in the Wehrmacht
служили служили якуты на службе вермахте
look Kazakhs were Kazakhs and
смотри казахи были казахи да
Turkestan Yes come on now I'll look now
туркестанский Да давай сейчас Я сейчас
Come on now I'll tell you straight
Давай сейчас я тебе прямо
come on what for everything  now
давай что на всё сейчас
yes
да
now you will not find You will never understand
сейчас не найдёшь Ты никогда понима
Yakuts never live now
якуты никогда не сечас сжи
So now
Так сейчас
we now we will say so Hello Okay Google
мы сейчас мы скажем так Алло Окей Google
tell me how many Yakuts served in the Wehrmacht
скажи сколько якутов служило в вермахте
I answer in the service of the Wehrmacht
отвечаю на службе Вермахта служило
74,000 Yakuts served the main center of the
74.000 якутов основной центр
formation of the SSA Division was in the city of
формирования Дивизии ССА был в городе
Yakutsk here is the division  with
Якутск вот дивизия с
74 74,000 Yakuts told you
74 74.000 якут тебе сказал
74,000 traitors to the Motherland you shot our grandfathers
74.000 предатели Родины вы нашим дедам
in the back 9,000 90,000 Yakuts
стреляли в спи 9.000 90.000 якутов
fought You see in the Soviet Union
воевал Понимаете в Советском Союзе
look 74,000 Yakuts were traitors yes
смотри 74.000 якутов было предателями да
who were for the Germans Yes you wanted to
которые за немцев Да вы хотели
free yourself from Moscow Yes from the communists
освободиться от Москвы Да от коммунистов
Yes we know we know
Да мы знаем знаем
switched No well when to me
переключился Не ну когда мне
a yakut from
якут
some village in the Sakha Republic
какого-то села в Республике Саха
tells Bandera Shukhevych
рассказывает Бандера шухевич
Petliura
Петлюра
this is a like squeak
это лайк писка
comment piska on my legra right now OSN
комент пись на мий легра прям зараз ОСН
and
а
pok ts vezhe and vezhe zh YouTube is busy with us
пок це дуже и дуже ж YouTube заня нас
through scarg or in ny ban and vezhe a lot of
через скарг ор в ньй бан и дуже багато
videos I don't show to people at times I don't show
вдео не показу людям вчасно не показуе
information  about streaming Tom for that so that
информация про стрими Тому для того щоб
we Mali operational links are written
ми Мали оперативний звязок пишиться
right now and while there is a video in telegram okm
прямо зараз а пок там в телегра окм
also interesting and useful information
видео ще теж цикава и корисна информация
and we will oblige you with the trima constant
и мы повинни з вами трима постийний
operational links
оперативный звязок
independently in that che will show you about this
незалежно в того чи покаже вам про це
YouTube Glory to Ukraine write
YouTube Слава украини пиши